波罗！波罗！
还真是不错，不过…
It's quite good,
他们在现实生活中可要英俊的多
but they are far more handsome in real life.
你在干吗？
What are you doing?
对不起，阁下，对不起，阁下，我只是在画你的肖像
Sorry, sir. Sorry, sir. Just taking your likeness, sir.
画我的肖像？
Taking my likeness?
你什么意思？快说，你个贼头贼脑的家伙！
What do you mean? Speak, thief!
阁下，艾文泰衣物染房行会
Sir, Aventine Cloth Dyers Association
雇我来
are paying me
画一幅你跟
to do a mural of you
乌瑞纳斯战斗在竞技场的画像
and Lucius vorenus in the arena, sir.
你给我说清楚为什么会有人这么做？
Explain yourself. Why would anybody do that?
为什么，阁下？
Why, sir?
你出名了，阁下
You're famous, sir.
到处都是你的画像
There's paintings of you all over.
但是那些都不如我画的像，阁下
Not good accurate ones like I'm gonna do, sir.
出名了？ 没错
Famous?  Certainly.
我？ 整个城市的人都为你疯狂
Me?  The whole city loves you, sir.
你跟乌瑞纳斯地方官
You and Magistrate vorenus
就是兄弟友爱互助的象征
are symbols of brotherly love and redemption.
如果你现在在罗马城的话，我很难相信会有哪位女士
If you were in Rome today, I doubt there's a lady in the city
不会为伟大的泰特斯·波罗敞开她房间的门
wouldn't open her doors for the mighty Titus Pullo.
可以放手了吗，阁下？
Would you let me go, please, sir?  Hmm? Oh.
Hmm.
很好，没错吧？
Beautiful, hmm?
直到河边为止这些地都是我们的
We own all of it, as far as the river.
真是太好了
Lovely.
最好适应一下这里
Best get used to it. Caesar might well
恺撒可能会把我从城中驱逐
exile me from the city.
就是因为你救了波罗？
Just for saving Pullo?  We'll live off the land like peasants.
我们就要农夫一样种田为生
他不会那么认真的  他可能会给予更严厉的惩罚
He wouldn't be so mean.  He might do far worse.
他会怎样？ 没什么
Like what?  Nothing.
我开玩笑的
I'm joking.
我不认为我们可以躺在毯子上
I don't suppose we can lay down a blanket.
我也不这么认为
I shouldn't think so.
好吧，如果我们以后要再这么做的话
Well, if we ever do this again,
我就不会穿上我最好的衣服了
I'm not wearing my best.
你们这些城里的女人，太娇贵了
Too soft, you city girls.
你住嘴，我已经躺在这了，对吧？
Hush you, I'm down here, aren't l?
在我冻死之前赶快上来
Get on with it before I die of cold.
我们要这样待多久？
How long like this?
直到祭司摇铃为止
Um, till the priest rings his bell.
女神保佑我
Juno help me.
这里的土很不错  潮湿而已
It's good earth, this.  It's wet earth.
又黑又肥，没有多少黏土
Dark, loamy, not much clay.
这样的土地上种什么长什么
You can grow anything in soil like this.
我们应该把农舍修到哪里？
Where should we build the farmhouse?
靠近水跟树林的山脊那边
That ridge over there. Close to the water and wood,
占据山谷的有利地形
good command of the valley.
如果有高卢人来打我们的话？
In case we get attacked by Gauls?
这都是说不准的
You never know.
这只是仪式，你应该假装…的
You're meant to be pretending.
我是在假装
I am.
你不是
You're not.
Shh shh.
到老爸这里来
Come to Papa.
贱货
Bitch.
你们的地怎么样？
Well, how was the farm?
克拉莉萨，等到你看到那片地的时候就知道它真是很好
Oh, Clarissa, wait till you see it. It's beautiful.
我肯定它很好
Oh, it's very fine, I'm sure.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
你们永远猜不到  我们永远猜不到
You'll never guess.  We'll never guess.
波罗从医院里跑了出来  什么？
Pullo ran away from the hospital.  What?
几个马车夫在阿匹恩附件发现了半死不活的他
Some carters found him lying half dead by the Appian.
他要他们带他到这里来  这儿？
He asked to be brought here.  Here?
他就在里面
He's inside.
掌管冥界的众神啊
Gods beneath us.
他根本就不应该站起来，更别说骑马了
He should not have been on his feet, never mind on a horse.
他所有的伤口都像鲜花一样绽开了
All his wounds have opened up, fresh as flowers.
真是个可怜的蠢货  我给他上了莨菪
Poor stupid thing.  I've given him
来止痛，并且把他固定在床上了
henbane to dull the pain and immobilize him.
如果他真能挺过来
If by any chance he lives,
最少十周天之内
he shouldn't move on any account
他是无论如何都不能动了
for at least 10 days and nights.
只要他一能够动我就把他送回乡下
I'll send him back to the country as soon as he is mobile.
就他目前这样，他不会再惹什么麻烦的
He won't cause any trouble, not like this.
就像以前那样
Like old times.
波罗
Pullo.
波罗？
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯，长官
Lucius vorenus, sir.
你在这里干吗？
What are you doing here?
我在哪里？ 罗马，在我家里
Where am l?  Rome, in my house.
你应该在艾文那的医院的
You should be in the hospital at Avernum.
那就错过了这些趣事了？为什么把我绑起来？
And miss all the fun? Why am I tied up--
什么有趣的事情？
What fun is that?
我们出名了，对吧？英雄
We're famous, aren't we? Heroes.
歌曲，戏剧
Songs, plays,
还有画到墙上的画像，对吧？
pictures on walls, eh?
你个该死的大惊小怪的蠢货，那又如何？
Damn foolish fuss. What of it?
你的脑子转的不够快啊，对吧？
You are a slow one, aren't you?
女人
Women.
没有什么比有名的人更加能够吸引她们的了
They like nothing better than a man with a big name.
拜托，你现在还活着就已经够运气了
Please. You are lucky to be breathing.
即使你能够熬到伤势复原
Even if you survive your wounds, Caesar will probably
恺撒都可能会把你再扔回竞技场
throw you back in the arena, and me with you.
而且还要我去作陪
你认为他会这么做？
Do you think he'll do that?
把我们俩再扔回竞技场？
Throw us back in?
明天就知道了，我明天要被召见
I'll find out tomorrow. I've been summoned.
他还说“女人”呢
"Women," he says.
如果你现在要一个女人
If you took a woman now,
你就会像一个旧袋子一样四分五裂了
you'd come apart like an old sack.
就像以前那样
Just like old times.
我无所谓
I don't mind.
能听到你父亲的笑声真是太好了
It's good to hear your father laughing for a change.
艾瑞纳
Eirene,
看到你真是太好了
it's good to see you.
很公平
Fair enough.
如果你下不了手
If you can't do it,
也没问题
that's all right too.
艾瑞纳！
Eirene,
你在干吗？-没什么
what are you doing?  Nothing. Nothing.
别骗我，你手里是什么？
Don't lie. What's that in your hand?
我们只是在聊天
We were just talking.
聊天？ 我也才知道
Talking?  Catching up.
你个傻瓜！
You fool! What if you killed him? What then?
如果你杀了他，你怎么办？
所有人都会知道是你做的
Everybody would know it was you.
一个自由女人杀了她的前任主人，真是太好了！
A freedwoman who killed her old master- very nice!
然后你去哪里，嗯？
And where would you go, hmm?
然后你怎么办？ 她说的没错
What would you do with yourself?  She has a point.
去睡觉
Go to bed. We'll say no more of this.
这件事到此为止
她看起来不错
She's looking well.
晚安，波罗
Good night, Pullo.
女神保佑你
Juno protect you.
别担心
Don't worry.
我不能让恺撒等我
I can't keep Caesar waiting.
艾瑞纳，你做完那个后去看看波罗敷的药
Eirene, when you finish that, check on Pullo's dressings
有必要的话就换
and change them if need be.  Me?
我？
You.
对，你
再喂他点粥
And feed him some porridge.
谢谢
Thank you.
今天
As of this day,
二月初一
the Kalends of February,
我们敬爱的元老独裁者
our beloved father dictator...
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒宣布
Gaius Julius Caesar has decreed
共和国元老院
that 100 new men be raised
要新增100名元老
to the Senate of the Republic.
二月初三
The third day before Nones,
要举行一个公共宴会
a public banquet will be held
以祝贺这些元老
to celebrate those senators.
奴隶跟自由人不许参加
Slaves and freedmen are not eligible.
任何再次扰乱秩序的人
Any repetition of recent disorders
都将受到严厉的惩罚
will be punished with severity.
我应该在这里改变河道，你看
I shall divert the river here, you see,
挖条运河到梵蒂冈山
by digging a canal to the vatican hills.
高！你应该改变河道
Splendid. You shall divert the river.
高！我对其起的作用毫无疑问
Splendid and useful, I have no doubt.
实际上，这样可以防止洪水
Indeed. It will prevent flooding
而且更容易到达武装集训场
and give easier access to the Fields of Mars.
在这片再生的土地上，我应该
And on the reclaimed land I shall build
为执政院再修些办公场所
new civic offices for the courts.
我还应该修
I shall also construct
一座维纳斯的神殿
a temple to venus Birthgiver.
又一个神殿…太好了
Another temple- excellent.
但是我们是否能够抽空谈谈
But if we might for the moment speak
这个…元老院…的扩大…？
of this expansion of the Senate?
我们可以
We might.  Ah.
高卢人跟凯尔特人，老男孩
Gauls and Celts, old boy.
长发的高卢人跟画成蓝脸的凯尔特人
Long-haired Gauls and blue-faced Celts.
你肯定是在开玩笑
You're joking, of course.
他不是在开玩笑
He is not joking.
高卢人跟凯尔特人？进入元老院？
Gauls and Celts? In the Senate?
从那些为罗马效劳最长时间的部落
From the tribes that have served Rome longest,
选择他们那些高尚人中最优秀的  我很吃惊
the best of their nobility.  I'm astonished.
很好
Good. Astonishment is my intent.
我就是想要你们吃惊
当前的大英雄来了
Ah, here comes the hero of the hour.
怎么了？没戴橡树叶的花圈？
What, no wreath of oak leaves?
那么，乌瑞纳斯，我现在应该怎么处理你？
Well now, vorenus, what am I to do with you?
藐视我定制的秩序，你竟然敢干扰
Defying my express orders, you dared interfere
一个通过法律裁定的死刑…
in a legally sanctioned execution--
完全是不服从以及犯罪的行为
an act of gross criminality and disobedience.
我深表歉意，长官，我没有任何借口
I humbly apologize, sir. I have no excuse.
你让我进退两难
You present me with a dilemma.
按正常的来说，我应该把你们扔到塔尔皮亚岩石之下
By right, I could have you thrown off the Tarpeian rock.
但是民众，思想简单
But the people, simple souls that they are,
已经把你跟波罗捧作英雄了
have made great heroes out of you and Pullo.
如果我要惩罚你的话
If I were to punish you,
会让民众变得极其愤怒
the people would be made extremely angry.
我不想让民众们愤怒
I do not wish to make the people angry,
因此，我不能惩罚你
ergo, I cannot punish you.
如果我不能惩罚你，我必须要奖励你
If I cannot punish you, I must reward you,
否则的话，我会让人感觉没有权威
else I shall seem weak.
现在，听听这个，西塞罗
Listen to this now, Cicero.
基于公众强烈的呼声
By popular acclaim,
我应该任命卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
I shall name Lucius Vorenus
成为罗马的一名元老
a Senator of Rome.
很好，对吧？
Good, eh?
现在，你们全都非常吃惊
Now you're all astonished.
乌瑞纳斯，你看起来就像看到了蛇发怪女一样
vorenus, you look like you've seen the Gorgon.
对不起，长官…
Excuse me, sir,
我太吃惊了
I'm stunned.
你怎么想的？
What do you say?
你会在元老院为你的人民说话吗？
Will you speak for your people in the Senate?
如果能这么做，我万分荣幸，但你真的认为我配当元老吗
I'd be honored to do so, if you think me worthy.
没有比你更相称的
There's none worthier.
你应该会成为一个杰出的元老
You shall make an excellent senator.
真是令人感动
very touching.
最开始的几个礼拜你要跟在我的身边
For the first few weeks, you will stay close by me.
学习那些规矩
Learn the drill.  Thank you, sir.
谢谢你，长官
Forgive me,
请原谅我，但是说真的，我必须作为一个朋友…
but really I must, as a friend--
我必须要抗议！
I must protest!
一个低贱的平民进入元老院？
A lowly pleb in the Senate?
这有点太过分了！
That's going too far.
并无冒犯你的意思，乌瑞纳斯
No offense to you, vorenus.
我不想再搞什么竞技场的东西了，西赛罗
I do not wish to jump in any arenas, Cicero.
我必须用别的方式来取悦民众
I must please the people in some other fashion.
再修一座神殿或者杀掉某个人
Build yet another temple. Kill someone.
人们很容易就会满足的
The people are easy to please.
但不是这个！
Not this.  I wish the Senate
我希望元老院里面是整个意大利最优秀的人
to be made of the best men in ltaly,
而不仅仅是罗马里这些有钱的老面孔
not just the richest old men in Rome.
一个非常有意思的想法
An intriguing notion.
你会让许多人非常生气
You'll make a lot of men very angry
都因为你提拔的那些高卢人，凯尔特人
with your Gauls and your Celts
那些平民等等
and your plebs and such.
我要加倍你的护卫队
I'll have to double your guard.
我已经跟他说过了，他会听吗？
That's what I told him. Will he listen?
护卫能够让我的敌人远离
Guards can keep my enemies away. They can do nothing
这样的话，他们就不能对我的朋友们做什么了
about my friends.  You don't mean me, do you?
你不会是指我吧？
I can assure you, I have no ill intentions.
我可以向你保证，我可没有什么不良企图
我知道
I know.
并不是你没有
Not that you were not perfectly capable
作恶的能力  谢谢
of any manner of wickedness.  Thank you.
而是如果你要背叛我 你在很久之前就应该已经做了
But if you were going to betray me, you would have done it long ago.
别以为我没有考虑过
Don't think I wasn't tempted.
那么，不增加护卫 你只能指望你的运气了
So, no more guards then. You will trust Fortune.
很好，很虔诚  别嘟嘟囔囔了
very good. very pious.  Stop your grizzling,
你这个老女人
you old woman.
谁敢动我一根手指头？
Who will dare raise a hand to me
有勇猛的卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯在我身边
with the ferocious Lucius vorenus at my side?
聪明
Ah. Clever.
跟我了这么多年你居然还是
All these years together, and it still surprises you
为我的能力感到吃惊
I can tie my sandals.
好好睡，小男人
Sleep sound, little man.
你母亲跟我一直在想
Your mother and l have been thinking
要给你找个丈夫
about finding you that husband.
一个元老的女儿不能
Asenator'sdaughter
老过着单身的生活
cannot be running around unattached.
不着急
Oh, there's no hurry.
别担心，我们会给你找到个有钱的老头子的
Don't worry, we'll find you a good rich old man
你只需要转动你的小手指
you can wrap around your little finger.
像你这种出色相貌的可有不少选择
Beauty like you can have your pick.
我跟你说过我不想嫁一个有钱的老头
I told you, I don't want a rich old man.
你当然想要 你想想看
Of course you do. Just think of all those
你能拥有的那些好衣服，珠宝跟奴隶
fine dresses and jewels and slaves you'll have.
我可不在乎这些不重要的东西
I don't care about such trivial things.
不重要？
Trivial?
我像你这么大的时候
When I was your age,
我只能啃沟里捡来的骨头
I had to eat bones from the gutter.
衣服跟珠宝可是非常重要的
Dresses and jewels are not trivial.
这些东西显示了你们
They show others that your people
有钱有权，而且
are rich and powerful and that you are
你受到了尊重，爱与保护
Ioved and protected and valued.
但我想嫁一个我爱的人
But I want to marry someone I love.
感情不是天生的，是需要培养的
Love doesn't come unbidden, you have to work for her.
如果你一开始就爱着那个男人，那你的婚姻才真是怪异的
Strange marriage it would be if you loved him from the start.
没错，需要点时间
That's right. It takes a while. Now you be a good
你成为了一个贞洁的好妻子，那么你就能赢得爱
virtuous wife, and love will come.
你母亲跟我我们过去有过问题，对吧？
Your mother and l, we had our troubles, didn't we?
看看我们现在
Look at us now.  Happy as you like.
非常快乐
I suppose.
我想是吧
So...
那么…
a good rich old man it is then.
说好了，一个有钱的老好男人
Hmm?
我正打算叫醒你
I was about to wake you.
不论你梦见了什么，肯定都不是一个好梦
Wherever you were, you were not enjoying yourself.
又一个有征兆的梦
It was another dream of omens.
你都快成神使了
You're becoming quite the oracle.
要我叫人拿点水吗？
Shall I send for some willow water?
你能睡得舒服点的  我梦见自己在乡村中
You'll sleep better.  I was in the country.
行了，我做那种梦，都做了好多年了
Please, I have had such dreams for years.
该死的雨，黑狗
Bloody rain, black dogs,
戴着头罩的船夫…好多年了
hooded ferrymen- for years.
看看我 还是活得很好
Here I am, still alive and well.
我以前从来没有过那样的梦
I've never had such dreams before now.
我应该怎么做？
What am I to do?
我是不是应该离开罗马并藏起来
Should I quit Rome and hide
就是因为你做的恶梦？
because you have bad dreams?
为什么不这么做？
Why not?
我是认真的
I'm serious.
你对这里辛苦的工作，难道不感到厌倦吗？
Are you not weary of this toil?
是的，我感到非常厌倦
I am. I am extremely weary.
但是有太多太多的事情要去做
But there is much more to be done,
不得不说，太多事情了
I'm afraid. Much more.
总有更多的事情要做
There's always more to be done.
怎么算到头？
To what end?
到头？
What end?
问的好
Good question.
我应该问问伯斯卡
I shall ask Posca.
睡吧，亲爱的
Go to sleep, my dear.
优利亚的先祖啊
AncestorsoftheJunii,
我们祈求你们的保佑
we ask for your blessing
保佑这个有着你们血脉的人
on this man of your blood.
让他更有力量
Let his arm be strong.
让他能达成他的目的
Let his aim be true.
让他的心中充满神圣的愤怒
Let his heart be filled with sacred rage.
好孩子
Good boy.
你好
Hello.
嗨，美女
Hey, venus,
我想问你个问题
I have a question for you.
猜猜我是谁
Guess who I am.
非常感激
Thanks very much.
能认识你真是很好
It was nice to meet you.
剩下的路我一个人就行了
I can manage from here.
等等
Wait.
嗯，大家都去哪儿了？
So, where is everybody?
我肯定我见过那个人在市场里卖鱼
I'm sure I saw that one selling fish in the Forum.
最起码他是个罗马人
Atleasthe's Roman.
一个好的罗马鱼贩相比那些
A good Roman fishmonger is a fine nobleman
自称为首领的比利时跟凯尔特人
compared to some of these Belgian and Celts
也能算的上真正的贵族了
that call themselves chiefs.
看那边就有一个，戴耳环的那个
There's one over there with earrings.
见到你真好
It's good to see you.
最后就是这样，嗯？
It's the end, eh?
高卢人进入到这里来了
The Gauls have invaded.
不要这么郁闷，他们会走的
Well, don't be so glum. They will return
很会就会回到他们山谷中那些丑陋的小屋中
to their ghastly mountain hovels soon enough.
恺撒只在需要他们支持一些有辱元老院
Caesar will only summon them back
的行为的时候才会召唤他们来
when he needs their support for some fresh outrage.
跟着恺撒的那个人
The red man shadowing Caesar is
我猜就应该是卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
the famous Lucius vorenus, one assumes.
没错  他们关系密切，对吧？
lndeed.  Affectionate, aren't they?
或许是父子
Might be father and son.
恺撒会让那个低贱的人这么想的
Caesar would have the humble people think so.
他总把那个卑贱的人带在身边
He keeps the wretched man by his side constantly.
那个战场上的禽兽居然是罗马的元老！
This beast of the fields is a Senator of Rome!
别这么烦恼，卡斯卡
Do not fret so, Casca.
我们这些屈服于恺撒王的胆小鬼
We timid subjects of King Caesar
必须要学会忍受，对吧？
must learn to be tolerant, hmm?
我想我应该回家
I believe I shall go home
通过喝酒来麻醉自己
and stupefy myself with wine.
祝你们好
Good day to you all.
老蠢货
Old fool.
他知道了，我敢肯定，他知道了 你看到了他看我们的样子
He knows, I'm sure of it. He knows. You saw how he looked at us.
冷静，辛伯 如果他知道了，我们早就应该死了
Be calm, Cimber. If he knew, we would be dead already.
他装作不知情 他在等待我们露出马脚
He's playing the blind man. He's waiting for us  to betray ourselves.
没错  他根本就不担心我们！
Exactly. He's not worried about us!
我把我们都想成胆小鬼
He thinks we are cowards.
那么，无论如何 我们必须要尽快行动
Well, in any case, we must act soon.
今天他让高卢人，凯尔特人跟平民进入元老院
Today he brings in Gauls and Celts and low plebs.
他以后就会让比利时人，自由人
Tomorrow it'll be Belgians or freedmen, and he won't rest
也进入元老院 不把元老院变成妓院
until he's turned the Senate into a bawdy house!
他是不会善罢罢休的！
那些外来的乌合之众就会从人数上超过我们这些高贵的贵族
We good noblemen will be outnumbered by foreign rabble.
我们将失去尊严
We will be degraded,
失去权力
powerless.
我们必须要尽快行动
We must act soon.  What about bloody Lucius vorenus?
那该死的卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯怎么办？
Lucius vorenus is a son of a whore.  You know him personally, it seems.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯是个杂种而已  听起来你认识他？
我认识他
I know him.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯是谁？
Who is Lucius vorenus?
目前，不知你是否记得有个
You remember, Mother, the low soldier
低贱的战士跳入竞技场就是为了救他的同伴？
that jumped into the arena to save a comrade?
我大概记得有这么回事
I remember something of the sort.
恺撒为了迎合大众让他当上了元老
Well, Caesar's pandered to the mob and made him a senator.
而且恺撒在元老院的时候
And when Caesar's in the Senate,
这条狗不离他主人左右
the dog never leaves his master's side.
而且是条可怕的狗
And afearsomedog itis.
所以…
So, if we are to reckon
如果我们要在元老院算计恺撒的话
with Caesar on the Senate floor,
我们必须把卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯也算计在内
we must reckon with Lucius vorenus also.
把他一起杀了，有什么问题？
Kill him as well. What's it matter?
他是个受欢迎的人
He is a popular man.
又如何？我会杀了他  我要让人们站在我们这边
So? I'll kill him.  It is most important
是非常重要的
that we keep the people on our side.
我们不能杀死他们的英雄
We cannot kill one of their heroes.
这会成为整个事件的污点的
That would sully the whole business.
只有暴君才…死
Only the tyrant dies.  Kill Caesar in his bed then. He
那么就在恺撒的床上把他解决了
doesn't sleep with this man, does he?  Quintus.
他不跟乌瑞纳斯一起睡，对吧？ 昆特斯！
还真不是个坏主意
It's not such a bad thought.
我们可以…买通一些他的奴隶
We could bribe some of his slaves.
收买他的厨子  收买他的试尝员毒死他
Buy off his cook. Buy off his taster. Poison him.
各位，我们可不是在讨论什么卑鄙的谋杀！
Gentlemen, this is not some cheap murder!
我们要做的是一件荣耀的事情
It is an honorable thing
所以必须要光明正大的去做
that we do, and it must be done honorably.
白天
In daylight.
在元老院里面
On the Senate floor.
我们自己动手
With our own hand.
包括我在内
With my hand.
是的，你是对的
You're right, of course.
请原谅我
Forgive me.
真是太好了
That's all very well,
但是怎么做呢？
but how?
怎么做呢？
How?
怎么了？
What's wrong?
你还没有睡着吗？
Are you still awake?
你在那里长吁短叹的…
You were worrying very loudly.
我感觉似乎一切都来得太快
I feel like everything seems to be moving so fast.
就好像…
It feels like--
我…
I'm--
我有时很害怕
I'm scared sometimes.
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯，那个是他的名字吗？ 什么啊？
Lucius vorenus, was that his name?  What?
恺撒提拔成元老的那个低贱的战士
The low soldier that Caesar made a senator.
那个是他的名字吗？
Was that his name?
卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯 怎么了？
Lucius vorenus. Why?
我以前听过他的名字
I have heard the name before.
“我亲爱的朋友
"My dear friend,
我为这段时间没有见到你们而感到惋惜
I regret I have not seen you or yours for some time.
像我们这样交织相缠的两个家族
Two families as entwined as ours
不应该成为陌路人
must not be strangers.
不知你明天是否能方便
Would it be convenient for you
到我这里来看我？
to come and visit me tomorrow?
为了我们长久的友谊，赛维莉娅”
With great affection, Servilia."
太奇怪了
How strange.
是吗？
Is it?
她为什么想见我？她恨我
Why would she want to see me? She hates me.
我也一样，那又不能阻止她向你示好
So do l. It's no bar to friendship.
她想什么呢？
What is she thinking?
肯定不是对你有好处的事情
Nothing to your benefit.
你会怎么做？ 我当然会答应
What will you do?  I shall accept, of course.
这么做明智吗？ 或许不
Is that wise?  Probably not.
她的愤怒使我愉快
Her rage amuses me.
你应该跟我一起去
You shall come with me.
为什么？ 当然是作为我的保护者
Why?  To be my protector, of course.
谁知道那个疯狂的老乌龟会做什么？
Who knows what the mad old turtle will do?
请不要这样说她
Please don't speak of her so.
但是她就是个疯狂的老乌龟
Well she is a mad old turtle.
无论怎样，我还以为你已经放低了那段低下的感情
Anyway, I thought you were above such petty emotions nowadays.
我是的，我努力去那么做
I am. I try to be.
你对她还有感觉
you still have feelings for her.
那也没什么错  我早已没有感觉了
There's nothing wrong with that.  I feel nothing
只是可怜她 也可怜那时候的我
but pity for her. And for myself as I was then.
也可怜你
And for you.
我？
Me?
你这只小笨鹅
You silly goose.
你为什么穿成这样？ 我要到城外去…
Why are you dressed so?  I'm going to the country--
只是今天而已 呼吸一下新鲜的空气
just for the day, to get some fresh air,
活动一下腿脚
stretch my legs.
我还想去一趟战场女神的神庙
I was thinking of stopping by the shrine of Sacred Rusina,
问问她是否能够原谅我做的那些坏事
asking her if she'll forgive me for all the bad things I've done.
你认为她会
You think she might?
原谅我吗？
Forgive me?
谁知道神会怎么答复你？
Who knows what the gods will do?
一起去 如果你想的话
Come along, if you like.
元老院今日集会
Senate in session today.
闲人不许在附近集会
No assemblies in the vicinity.
不允许赌博 不允许卖淫
No gaming. No prostitution.
愿所有的神都保佑我们神圣的长者
May all the gods bless our sacrosanct father
盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
Gaius Julius Caesar.
你好，元老  你好
Good day, Senator.  Good day.
长官，长官，请给我点时间！
Sir, sir, a moment of your time!
看看我的陈情书！
Read my petition!
恺撒！恺撒！恺撒！
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
我亲爱的阿提娅
My dear Atia,
看到你真是太好了
how wonderful to see you.
真是太好了
Wonderful indeed.
还有你，屋大维！
And Octavian!
你都快成为一个男人了！
You're practically a man!
我也这么想
I like to think so.
而且还这么英俊 进来，进来
And so handsome. Come in, come in.
这里看起来很好
It's looking lovely here.
你是否重新装饰过了？
Have you redecorated?
拉！
Pull!
拉！ 拉！
乌瑞纳斯元老
Senator vorenus,
我是为了你的孙子而来的，卢西尔斯
I come about your grandson Lucius.
优利亚家的赛维莉娅，而且我现在跟你说的
...Servilia of the Junii, and what I tell you now
都是真的
is the truth.
你还活着！
You're alive!
回答我，那个孩子是怎么回事？
Answer me, what child is that?
乌瑞纳斯在哪里？
Where is vorenus?
他刚才还跟我们在一起
He was with us a moment ago.
无所谓了
Never mind.
马克·安东尼，能跟我们谈一会吗？
Mark Anthony, why don't you give us a moment?
你肯定在想今天我为什么邀请你到这里
You must be wondering why I invited you here today.
我还真是有些不解
I am rather puzzled.
其实，对我来说是非常重要的
Well, it's important to me
我成为第一个告诉你
that I be the first to tell you
发生了什么事情的人
what has happened.
为什么？发生什么事情了？
Why? What has happened?
曲巴尼尔斯  伟大的恺撒
Trebonius.  Great Caesar.
我知道，巴卡，我明白 我没有忘记
I know, Barca, I know. I have not forgotten.
和蔼的恺撒，如果我可以的话
If I may, gracious Caesar,
请您考虑一下赦免我兄弟的流放
you were going to consider revoking my brother's exile.
我还在考虑中
I'm still considering it.
把你的手拿开
Take your hand off me.
你们还在等什么？就是现在了！现在！
What are you waiting for? Now! Now!
现在！ 现在！
Now.  Now!
等等！ 放开我！
Wait!  Get off me!
动手吧
Do it.
住手！
Stop it!
怎么了？
What's wrong?
他在哪里？ 谁啊？
Where is he?  Who?
你儿子！
Your son!
告诉我这不是真的
Tell me it's not true.
告诉我！告诉我！
Tell me! Tell me!
告诉我！
Tell me.
我当时以为你死了
I thought you were dead.
卢西尔斯
Oh Lucius.
Lucius.
卢西尔斯
Lucius,
这个孩子是无罪的
the boy is blameless.
暴君永远的下场
Thus ever for tyrants.
不！
No!
那么你看，暴君死了
So you see, the tyrant is dead,
而且你又没有后台了 又恢复了共和
the Republic is restored, and you are alone.
你想要点蜜水吗？
Would you like some honey water?
不用，谢谢
I won't, thank you.
请不要担心，我不会伤害你的
Please don't be afraid. I won't harm you.
还不到时候
Not yet.
伤害？
Harm?
你为什么想要我们受到伤害？
Why would you wish us harm?
我们一直都是好朋友
We've always been great friends.
政治是男人的事情，我一直… 还没到时候
Politics is for the men, I always-  Not yet.
我会慢慢折磨你的
I will make you suffer slowly.
慢慢的，深深的
Slowly and deeply,
正如你折磨我一样
as you made me suffer.
首先，我想看到你逃跑
First, I want to see you run.
为了生命而逃跑
Run for your life.
跑到希腊
Run to some rathole
或者伊利里亚的某个角落
in Greece or lllyria,
无论哪里你想去
wherever you like.
我都会跟着去找到你
I shall come and find you.
感谢你的拜访
Thank you for the visit.
翻译:TLF字幕组